<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri - Freelance Programmer - Linux, Technology</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/feeds/linux-technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prahladyeri.com/</id><updated>2017-07-05T04:21:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>How to install Debian+LXDE on ANY Android Tablet</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2017/07/install-debian-lxde-on-tablet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-05T04:21:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-07-05T04:21:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2017-07-05:/blog/2017/07/install-debian-lxde-on-tablet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Running a linux distro on android devices is a hot topic these days, and why not? After all, android is already based on linux kernel, but a pretty much locked-down and dumbed-down version of it. The OEM doesn’t give you root and in most cases, not even an open …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Running a linux distro on android devices is a hot topic these days, and why not? After all, android is already based on linux kernel, but a pretty much locked-down and dumbed-down version of it. The OEM doesn’t give you root and in most cases, not even an open source bootloader or kernel.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way, its good for maybe the most average user who doesn’t care about the OS and just want to use their phones. But for a power user, that’s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/2017/07/debian_xfce_tablet.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Debian (LXDE) running on Xiaomi MiPad" class="size-full wp-image-553" src="/uploads/2017/07/debian_xfce_tablet.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Debian (LXDE) running on Xiaomi MiPad Tablet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The so called apps available in the Play Store don’t allow you to utilize the full power of your linux device. A power user always wants to have the power of a full linux distro (such as Debian or Ubuntu or Fedora) on his/her device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I researched for the best way to install a linux distro on a tablet, preferably one that didn’t involve rooting or partitioning the device. The &lt;a href="https://wiki.debian.org/ChrootOnAndroid"&gt;debian guide&lt;/a&gt; lists down several methods and apps to do this such as Linux Deploy, GNURoot, Termux, etc. Out of them, the least risky and one that supports most android devices (including my KitKat tablet) is &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.gnuroot.debian"&gt;GNURoot-Debian&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you install this app on your tablet, it creates a self-contained &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;chroot&lt;/code&gt; install of debian using a tool called &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Proot"&gt;Proot&lt;/a&gt;. Once that is done, all you need to do is open up the app terminal and just start using it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;apt-get update
apt-get install tmux vim gcc python python3 python3-pip
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, these are just some of the packages that I’ve installed, you can do whatever you want with your linux installation. The only limitation is regarding multiple user logins. By default, the app will login you as &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; and while you can create additional users using &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;useradd&lt;/code&gt; command, don’t expect things like &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;setuid&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;setgid&lt;/code&gt; to work. The only way to switch user is using the &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;su - yourLogin&lt;/code&gt; command (whilst the &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;login&lt;/code&gt; command should work too in theory, I’m having a few problems with it presently, it might need some fixing in /etc/pam.d/* configuration files).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, if you have good amount of RAM on your tablet, you may consider using a desktop environment along with your headless installation (LXDE is recommended as it performs best on minimal resources). In order to do that, you’ll need two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=x.org.server&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;XServer-XSDL app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LXDE/XFCE desktop installed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former is used to interact with the headless XServer installation of your debian and provide you a graphical desktop environment. For the latter, you’ll have to just &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;apt-get install lxde&lt;/code&gt; (or lxde-core depending on your choice). Then, in order to use the desktop any time on your tablet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Open XServer-XSDL app, follow the instructions until you reach a blue screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Go to the debian installation and run:\
export DISPLAY=:0 PULSE_SERVER=tcp:127.0.0.1:4712\
startlxde &amp;amp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) Go back to XServer-XSDL app to interact with the desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, you should be able to see an lxde desktop like the one shown in the above screen. Coupled with the keyboard case and a bunch of great linux apps (such as vim, emacs, geany, inkscape, eclipse, etc.), you should be able to convert your mobile tablet into a great development machine on wheels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.xda-developers.com/guide-installing-and-running-a-gnulinux-environment-on-any-android-device/"&gt;https://www.xda-developers.com/guide-installing-and-running-a-gnulinux-environment-on-any-android-device/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.debian.org/ChrootOnAndroid"&gt;https://wiki.debian.org/ChrootOnAndroid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.gnuroot.debian"&gt;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.gnuroot.debian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=x.org.server&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=x.org.server&amp;amp;hl=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Proot"&gt;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Proot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Android"></category><category term="Debian"></category><category term="LXDE"></category></entry><entry><title>How to assemble a fast and minimal Debian Desktop using Openbox</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2016/02/minimal-debian-desktop-setup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-16T07:23:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-16T07:23:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2016-02-16:/blog/2016/02/minimal-debian-desktop-setup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being a web developer, one of the nagging things to do is keeping your hardware in sync with your performance requirements. In the good old times, a &lt;code&gt;P4&lt;/code&gt; or even a &lt;code&gt;Celeron&lt;/code&gt; based PC or laptop was enough for programming. But with changing times, the required investment to get a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being a web developer, one of the nagging things to do is keeping your hardware in sync with your performance requirements. In the good old times, a &lt;code&gt;P4&lt;/code&gt; or even a &lt;code&gt;Celeron&lt;/code&gt; based PC or laptop was enough for programming. But with changing times, the required investment to get a sane performance has increased to astronomical levels.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem is not just with the limitations of hardware, but our requirements too have increased. Apart from the tons of most needed apps like &lt;code&gt;eclipse&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;firefox&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;libreoffice&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;thunderbird&lt;/code&gt;, etc., you now have to keep VMs running in &lt;code&gt;virtualbox&lt;/code&gt; at the same time you are having a chat on &lt;code&gt;skype&lt;/code&gt; with your client. Add to that, &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt; things like &lt;code&gt;eclipse&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Android Emulator&lt;/code&gt; and your linux (or even Windows) desktop will start to buckle under the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, even an Intel &lt;em&gt;i5&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;i7&lt;/em&gt; chip isn’t sufficient today to handle multiple heavy or memory consuming apps. The only solution I have found is to use a lighter window-manager like &lt;code&gt;Openbox&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Fluxbox&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;IceWM&lt;/code&gt; instead of a heavy Desktop Environment like &lt;code&gt;GNOME&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Unity&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;KDE&lt;/code&gt;. This tutorial contains all the steps needed to assemble on your own light-weight DE based on &lt;code&gt;Openbox&lt;/code&gt; on Debian (or one of its compatible derivatives like Ubuntu or Linux Mint).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Openbox" class="size-full wp-image-498" height="537" src="/uploads/2016/02/openbox.png" width="956"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Openbox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://openbox.org"&gt;Openbox&lt;/a&gt; is an open source project (GPL licensed) based on the good old blackbox. It provides just the minimal framework to build a no-flashy, sane desktop environment that gets out of your way, so most resources are used for running the &lt;em&gt;actual apps&lt;/em&gt; that you use. Openbox occupies less than 8 MB of RAM on your machine. Again, this kind of setup is not for everyone, in case you are a huge fan of the Unity dash or GNOME dash, you may not like Openbox at all. On the other hand, if you like the new MATE Desktop which is based on the old GNOME 2, you may find this approach interesting. In fact, Openbox is the window manager used by &lt;code&gt;LXDE&lt;/code&gt;, the DE most famous for being light on resources. You are, in fact, going to create something like your own version of &lt;code&gt;LXDE&lt;/code&gt; by following this tutorial, only its even more minimal and custom to your requirements. Here is how to do it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the Debian minimal net-install ISO from &lt;a href="https://www.debian.org/CD/netinst/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is roughly 150-200 MB in size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either burn the &lt;code&gt;ISO&lt;/code&gt; to a USB drive or try it out in a VM first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the text based or graphical installer to complete the installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you land on the command line, login as the superuser (&lt;code&gt;su&lt;/code&gt;) and install these packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;apt-get install network-manager
apt-get install xorg openbox xdm
apt-get install xbacklight pcmanfm lxappearance lxpanel gmrun gnome-terminal
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the panel automatically show up, add this to &lt;code&gt;~/.config/openbox/autostart&lt;/code&gt; file using &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; editors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;lxpanel &amp;amp;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this will create only a &lt;em&gt;bare minimum&lt;/em&gt;, workable DE with just a File Manager and no other usable apps. lxpanel is a “Windows-98 style” panel that sits on top/bottom of your desktop and gives a “start-menu” in which your programs are organized. lxappearance is a handy tool to switch GTK themes which comes very useful. You still have to install &lt;code&gt;evince&lt;/code&gt; to read PDF books, &lt;code&gt;geany&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;gedit&lt;/code&gt; for a GUI text editor, &lt;code&gt;iceweasel&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;icedove&lt;/code&gt; for a browser and mail client respectively, and &lt;code&gt;libreoffice-calc&lt;/code&gt; for a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the good thing is that you are the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; of your desktop world now. You don’t have to live with that extra load of bloated baggage that heavy DEs usually come with. If you follow the above process correctly, you will end up with an installation size of less than 500 MB! And your own custom-made DE that works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for customization, &lt;code&gt;Openbox&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;a href="http://openbox.org/wiki/Help:Configuration"&gt;highly customizable&lt;/a&gt;. Arch Linux also has a wonderful &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/openbox"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; on this topic, and &lt;a href="https://www.maketecheasier.com/configure-andcustomize-openbox/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is another brief guide. For menus, you can either install &lt;code&gt;obmenu&lt;/code&gt; or if you are a simplicity fan like me, you can just edit your way through &lt;code&gt;~/.config/openbox/menu.xml&lt;/code&gt;. This, and the other file, &lt;code&gt;~/.config/openbox/rc.xml&lt;/code&gt; are the only two Openbox configuration files and they have all the needed options. In fact, if you decide to make use of the &lt;code&gt;lxpanel&lt;/code&gt; main menu, you don’t even have to edit the &lt;code&gt;menu.xml&lt;/code&gt; of Openbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lxpanel&lt;/code&gt; is not the only option for installing a Desktop panel, there are others too like &lt;code&gt;fbpanel&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tint2&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xfce4-panel&lt;/code&gt;. Read &lt;a href="https://www.maketecheasier.com/configure-andcustomize-openbox/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a battery indicator to the &lt;code&gt;lxpanel&lt;/code&gt;, add this to the &lt;code&gt;~/.config/lxpanel/default/panels/panel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Plugin {
  type = batt
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save your openbox customizations between sessions (which is a basic requirement), copy the &lt;code&gt;rc.xml&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;menu.xml&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;/etc/X11/openbox&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;~/.config/openbox/&lt;/code&gt; (create this folder if it doesn’t exist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmrun&lt;/code&gt; is needed to show the run dialog that pops up when you press &lt;code&gt;Alt+F2&lt;/code&gt; in any “normal” DE. Once you install &lt;code&gt;gmrun&lt;/code&gt;, just add below code to &lt;code&gt;~/.config/openbox/rc.xml&lt;/code&gt; somewhere in the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;keyboard&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; section, in order to make the keys work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!--start: Prahlad--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;keybind&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;key=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;A-F2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;action&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Execute&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;command&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;gmrun&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/command&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/action&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/keybind&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!--end: Prahlad--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdm&lt;/code&gt; is optional, but helpful if you don’t want to do a lot of configuration changes in &lt;code&gt;xorg&lt;/code&gt; files to show up the desktop automatically each time you login. Of course, you can use &lt;code&gt;lightdm&lt;/code&gt; too if you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don’t use bluetooth a lot and haven’t included any of those packages, but there are many of them such as &lt;code&gt;bluez&lt;/code&gt; in case you need one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://openbox.org/wiki/Help:Configuration"&gt;Openbox Wiki - Configuration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/openbox"&gt;Arch Linux Openbox docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.maketecheasier.com/configure-andcustomize-openbox/"&gt;Make Tech Easier - Openbox configuration guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.debian.org/CD/netinst/"&gt;Debian Netinstall Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=156272"&gt;lxpanel Battery Indicator installation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Debian"></category><category term="Linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux Desktop Survey Project - Feb/2016</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2016/02/linux-desktop-survey-project-feb2016.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-07T21:23:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-07T21:23:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2016-02-07:/blog/2016/02/linux-desktop-survey-project-feb2016.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will start this post by thanking the kind folks at the Reddit’s &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/linux"&gt;linux subreddit&lt;/a&gt; and Voat’s &lt;a href="https://www.voat.co/v/linux"&gt;linux subverse&lt;/a&gt; who wholeheartedly participated in this survey. &lt;a href="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/index.php/statistics_user/action/surveyid/556933/language/en"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; are the results and they are pretty insightful. For a developer who builds apps targetting the linux platform, it helps to know …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will start this post by thanking the kind folks at the Reddit’s &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/linux"&gt;linux subreddit&lt;/a&gt; and Voat’s &lt;a href="https://www.voat.co/v/linux"&gt;linux subverse&lt;/a&gt; who wholeheartedly participated in this survey. &lt;a href="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/index.php/statistics_user/action/surveyid/556933/language/en"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; are the results and they are pretty insightful. For a developer who builds apps targetting the linux platform, it helps to know what are the preferences of users who run those apps on a desktop. Not understanding these requirements beforehand has caused a lot of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unity_%28user_interface%29"&gt;unneeded backlash&lt;/a&gt; in the history of linux desktop development and a lot many forks were created which ended up causing a division of focus.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did I learn a lot about what the linux desktop users want in general, but the survey also threw some light on what distros or desktop environments are generally perceived to be either giving a better performance or providing a better user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the most important factor when choosing a Distro?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Linux Desktop Survey Project" src="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/tmp/ec2d620c7c97d4d351ad3553d3dc4161.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were the options I had set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better Performance and speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better User Experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Mix of both&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prevailing assumption of a lot many people is that linux users are usually those “super nerdy” tech geeks who are only interested in arcane things like computing performance and speed. But on the contrary, we learn that linux users are just like &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;Windows&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;OSX&lt;/code&gt; users for that matter, and they prefer a better user experience over performance!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, most of the folks preferred a balance of both performance and user experience. In fact, &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;Better Performance and speed&lt;/code&gt; was the least favored factor for most people who chose their distros, which implies that how wrong our assumptions sometimes could be! As one redditor said, I should have included &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;Software Freedom&lt;/code&gt; as an option since that is also quite a motivating factor for a lot many linux users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two comments from participants who chose the middle-path, &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;A Mix of both&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel I have to compromise on one or the other. A good user experience also encompasses acceptable performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good UX is crucial for my own comfort, but the speed and performance must be reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what the undecided folks (Other) have to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While user experience is very important, I feel this is for nought if it is not matched with upstream packages. I find it terribly tedious to find myself on a distro which is lagging behind on the likes of gnome-shell and firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full choice over programs and user interface; my own OS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability and security are the most important factors for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option I should have added here was &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;Stability and security&lt;/code&gt; since these are the very foundations upon which linux sits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;People’s Favorite Distro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Most Popular Distro" src="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/tmp/dfdd05e767cc742c456552f065121e8c.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu’s popularity is pretty well-known in the linux world, but what surprised me was Arch. Perhaps, it was the bias effect of lot many people on linux subbredit being Arch fans, or maybe Arch users have actually increased relative to Ubuntu during recent years, who knows! In any case, this survey result does indicate to me that if tomorrow I were to develop a linux destop app, then which distros should I test on with some priority. This is just one of the benefits of conducting this survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few user comments in this category:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually Arch derivative Antergos. This distribution has good a user experience and it is performant. It also delivers fresh software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Debian on my desktop, Arch as a DOM0 on my server, and RHEL/CENTOS at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly hate the linux desktop. It has so many bugs and is visually very hard to parse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Distro with Best Performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Distro with Best Performance" src="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/tmp/2784dfd5801a114e64e2de0393a8d1e9.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the Phronix arcane performance benchmarks, I thought about asking the users directly which Distro gave them the best performance. I don’t doubt the benchmarks, but computing is such a complex phenomena that raw performance isn’t as much an indicator of overall performance as it used to be in the past. Besides, the best proof of pudding is in the eating. Linux enthusiasts distro-hop a lot and in that process learn about the distros a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, Arch was at top here, followed by Gentoo. Debian came third which was not at all surprising. In fact, I expected this vanilla of a distro to be on the top. Perhaps the “Arch fans” effect of linux subreddit again! What surprised me, however, was Fedora coming such low on performance score. Here is what the participants had to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crunchbang (development started so name changed to Busenlabs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no idea but xubuntu runs ok on a dual core laptop from 2007 with 2gb of ram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First benchmarks, then if no existing distro fits the bill, Gentoo, Yocto project, or LFS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tested a number of distros on a very slow AMD netbook and Mint with Cinnamon was faster than itself and others with XFCE and MATE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If performance was the only criteria, I would use windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably, arch. Whichever one isn’t in the hands of the NSA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Which Distro gives the Best User Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Which Distro gives the Best User Experience" src="http://lws-rmsreturns.rhcloud.com/limesurvey/tmp/43ddb58e40e9ececf0e0ed58c106e182.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu is most people’s favorite in this area, but Ubuntu’s community clone &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/code&gt; bagging away the top position is also a fitting thing. Like Ubuntu, Mint is a distro which happens to “just work” according to most users. Though I personally don’t like all the extra amount of non-free codecs and plugins it comes pre-bundled with (such as Flash and Adobe), it is a good distro for existing Windows users to hop on. Here is what participants have to say about choosing the distro which provides the best user experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mint is great out of the box and requires minimal configuration to “just work”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enhanced user experience means more convenience and more toys; Ubuntu repos cover both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arch derivative Antergos. Just enough training wheels to be easy, still all the goodness of Arch. Why not Ubuntu? Ubuntu is bloated and stale and only has the name of being easiest. While once true, the competition has caught up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows (See the same answer under the “performance” question.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mint does a very good job of providing the right apps to control settings, out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy to use (Linux Mint), comes with programs that I’m familiar with (Firefox, Thunderbird, LibreOffice) and the interface is simple but also powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allows heavy customization to how I want it (Gentoo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purely for ease of use/install (Ubuntu).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haven’t tried that many but of of the few that I have tried Mint has had the most clear and logical meny items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the many enthusiastic distro-hoppers, my search for the discovery of best linux desktop continues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Linux"></category></entry></feed>