<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri - Freelance Programmer - Technology</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prahladyeri.com/</id><updated>2019-05-16T19:59:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Growing intolerance and lack of compassion towards new developers on StackOverflow</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2019/05/growing-intolerance-and-lack-of-compassion-towards-new-developers-on-stackoverflow.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-16T19:59:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-16T19:59:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2019-05-16:/blog/2019/05/growing-intolerance-and-lack-of-compassion-towards-new-developers-on-stackoverflow.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;StackOverflow is the digital equivalent of the Holy See or the Holy Mecca when it comes to programming. It is that place where developers go visit when they don't have answers to their coding problems in a hope that the Gods of StackOverflow will help them solve it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lately …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;StackOverflow is the digital equivalent of the Holy See or the Holy Mecca when it comes to programming. It is that place where developers go visit when they don't have answers to their coding problems in a hope that the Gods of StackOverflow will help them solve it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lately, the Gods of StackOverflow seem to be exhibiting a lot of intolerance and impatience towards those who are still learning the craft of programming and new to it. There seems to be a growing belief or consensus that unless you already have a certain level of expertise, you don't belong here in our chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example of this dude today who had &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/56167254/disable-enable-submit-button-when-clicking-on-checkbox-using-jinja2-templating"&gt;a very simple question about jinja2 templates&lt;/a&gt;, a topic related to flask, a python web framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A question about jinja2, abruptly closed as a duplicate" class="wp-image-1132 size-large" height="458" src="/uploads/2019/05/so_closed_incorrectly-1024x458.png" width="1024"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A question about jinja2 abruptly closed as a duplicate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was about to answer this question when it was abruptly closed for being a duplicate. The person who closed this didn't even consider that a beginner coder (considering the reputation score) may not even know what the capabilities of jinja2 were. How the heck was s/he supposed to know that the answer to this question was to be found outside the context of jinja2? Everyone on this planet isn't a born expert in web development. The coder expected a solution in the context of jinja2 templates itself and the right way would have been to guide him/her and explain that this isn't possible through jinja2 but front-end scripting is required here. Then the answering post could proceed to provide a few helpful example links from StackOverflow or someplace else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to ask those intolerant ones: consider that you yourself could have needed this hand-holding and guidance when you were beginning to code some years earlier? Just because coding has become so easy and second nature to you now, it doesn't give you any right to behave with arrogance. Knowledge needs to be used with grace and caution, with power comes the responsibility of using that power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of behavior is quite common from what I've been reading lately on social media too and my observation today just confirms it. I hope that more and more senior developers develop compassion towards others and treat this site as the temple of knowledge which it really is, not an egotistical chamber to shut down other programmers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Flask"></category><category term="JavaScript"></category><category term="Web Development"></category><category term="Social Networking"></category></entry><entry><title>A Dark Day For Consumer Rights - Right To Repair Bill Killed In Canada Thanks To Corporate Lobbying</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2019/05/a-dark-day-for-consumer-rights-right-to-repair-bill-killed-in-canada-thanks-to-corporate-lobbying.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-03T14:23:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-03T14:23:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2019-05-03:/blog/2019/05/a-dark-day-for-consumer-rights-right-to-repair-bill-killed-in-canada-thanks-to-corporate-lobbying.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When Linus Torvalds wrote the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"&gt;Linux Kernel&lt;/a&gt; in 1991 or Ian Murdock first released the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debian"&gt;Debian OS&lt;/a&gt; in 1993, talking about the "openness" of a PC or the "right to repair it" would have been a laughable affair! 8086 was an open standard then (just as standards should be) and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When Linus Torvalds wrote the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"&gt;Linux Kernel&lt;/a&gt; in 1991 or Ian Murdock first released the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debian"&gt;Debian OS&lt;/a&gt; in 1993, talking about the "openness" of a PC or the "right to repair it" would have been a laughable affair! 8086 was an open standard then (just as standards should be) and anybody was free to write an operating system for it (such as Linux), or user land utilities (such as GNU) or even define a desktop standard (such as Xorg).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="random image" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-904" height="225" src="/uploads/2018/07/pexels-photo-261577-300x225.jpeg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in 2019, that's no longer the case with standards. Looks like humanity is going backward in terms of progress as standards are becoming more and more closed and proprietary instead of becoming open and transparent. Companies like Apple are successful in not only creating entire dependencies of such closed standards but are fighting tooth and nail so that their closed standards get a stamp from the legislature too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law makers of Ontario, Canada succumbed to this massive corporate lobbying today and &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/9kxayy/right-to-repair-bill-killed-after-big-tech-lobbying-in-ontario"&gt;killed the "right to repair" bill before it could even see the lights of the day&lt;/a&gt;. This bill was asking for a very basic thing - the right to open your own device (which you've already paid for) and fix it for any problems. In order to empower a user to do this, the bill called for forcing tech companies like Apple to provide the following at a fair price:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repair Manual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Official Parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diagnostic Tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something very basic, something the Stallmans and Torvalds of the world have already been doing since 90s. Canada sent a very wrong signal to the tech world today, this would have been the first such pro-consumer law in the world, if passed. &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/evex8z/right-to-repair-advocates-are-hosting-youtube-town-halls-to-show-you-how-to-get-involved-in-the-movement"&gt;About 20 American states are also considering a similar right to repair bill&lt;/a&gt; and this sets a very wrong precedent to those decision makers. Both USA and Canada are highly developed countries and the whole world looks up to them for framing their own tech laws, so this is a very bad thing that happened today. I hope the American states will act sanely and pass this bill otherwise any hope left for open standards and protocols for the future generations will be lost. Since innovation blossoms in openness and gets stifled in closed environments, this will sound a death knell to innovation too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is now left to organizations like &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/"&gt;EFF&lt;/a&gt; and internet freedom activists like &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/"&gt;Richard Stallman&lt;/a&gt; to protest this decision and ensure some sanity in the tech world which is getting increasingly crony capitalistic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="Open Source"></category></entry><entry><title>Foxy Firefighters And The Clash Between Individual And Collective Liberalism</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2019/02/foxy-firefighters-and-the-clash-between-individual-and-collective-liberalism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-02T10:51:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-02T10:51:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2019-02-02:/blog/2019/02/foxy-firefighters-and-the-clash-between-individual-and-collective-liberalism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The biggest speculation in the tech industry these days concern net neutrality and the last week was no different. Whilst I'm happy that TRAI is clear on upholding the net neutrality in my own country, India, the clouds of doom could be clearly seen in USA as the FCC is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The biggest speculation in the tech industry these days concern net neutrality and the last week was no different. Whilst I'm happy that TRAI is clear on upholding the net neutrality in my own country, India, the clouds of doom could be clearly seen in USA as the FCC is trying hard to banish net neutrality and bring control of the Internet in the hands of a few large companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite worrying for Internet in general because the world looks up to the United States for laws governing the digital space, not India. What's hilarious is that the FCC is resorting to unbelievable arguments like &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2019/02/throttling-of-firefighters-hurts-fcc-case-as-it-defends-net-neutrality-repeal/"&gt;broadband isn't a telecommunication service&lt;/a&gt; in their desperate attempt to repeal net neutrality. I hope the US legal system is smart enough to discard such illogical arguments and the light of justice prevails in the country where Internet was first invented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="random laptop image" class="size-medium wp-image-1087 aligncenter" height="200" src="/uploads/2019/02/laptop-1478822_1920-300x200.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The positive thing though is that those fighting on the side of net neutrality are also strong in numbers and include &lt;a href="https://9to5mac.com/2019/02/01/save-net-neutrality/"&gt;companies like Reddit, Mozilla, Vimeo, etc. along with 22 state attorneys&lt;/a&gt;. Also, unbelievably, in the middle of this protest against repeal of net neutrality are a &lt;a href="https://abcnews.go.com/beta-story-container/Business/firefighters-join-mozilla-net-neutrality-fight-citing-public/story?id=60750432"&gt;bunch of fire fighters&lt;/a&gt; who also want net neutrality to prevail! Fire fighters of California are citing public safety as a reason to uphold net neutrality and logically so. According to the linked ABC news report, California witnessed the largest fire in its entire history and the firefighters encountered an unexpected danger - they couldn't communicate with their team members as Verizon was deliberately throttling and slowing down Internet speed on their phones. This is just a small sample of what could happen across the world if net neutrality was repealed for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2019/1/29/18202880/facebook-research-enterprise-root-certificate-onavo-techcrunch"&gt;Facebook seems to be offering teenagers 20/month in exchange for their phone activity data&lt;/a&gt;. While privacy advocates are all pitchforks on this happening and calling for Facebook to be made liable, this has a very large implication on the ever ongoing debate on &lt;strong&gt;"Individual Liberty vs Collective Liberty"&lt;/strong&gt;. For me, personally, it makes sense that digital privacy is a very important thing and online companies shouldn't be encouraged by allowing to run schemes like these when studies have shown that they already collect a whole lot of user data by default (location tracking, analytics, diagnostic data, etc.). Any other ration dude who has some knowledge of Information Technology will also think similarly, I suppose. However, if I try to advocate this knowledge to others and call for laws preventing such individual sale of private data, we are venturing into the area of collective liberalism, and here comes the danger of a clash happening between collective and individual liberalism. The thing is that those teenagers (however misguided they are), have full liberty to trade their private data with facebook or whatever social media company they want, and preventing them from doing that might be against the ethics of individual liberalism, that's just my few cents. In all probability, this debate could continue for years to come and so will the privacy debate, hopefully a solution will be found which is favorable and acceptable to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not the least, there are &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/feb/01/facebook-mental-health-study-happiness-delete-account"&gt;many studies like&lt;/a&gt; these sprouting up these days claiming that deleting Facebook or Twitter accounts bring happiness in people's lives. However, I want someone to perform another study into the mystery of why do so many people decidedly stay unhappy by constantly plugging into the social media sites!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Docker Trick: Running Containers Efficiently Using A Bash Script</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/09/docker-trick-running-containers-efficiently-using-a-bash-script.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-14T10:59:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-14T10:59:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-09-14:/blog/2018/09/docker-trick-running-containers-efficiently-using-a-bash-script.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the basic problems with running a docker image is that its too easy to spew up multiple instances or containers of the same image. Consider running the following container for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker run -it -e AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; -e AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; \
--net=host &amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; /bin/bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the basic problems with running a docker image is that its too easy to spew up multiple instances or containers of the same image. Consider running the following container for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker run -it -e AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; -e AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; \
--net=host &amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; /bin/bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will start a fresh container instance from image &lt;strong&gt;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&lt;/strong&gt; and you may optionally pass environment variables (using -e switch), and the /bin/bash argument to manually trigger a command inside the container instead of running the default one. However, once you exit the container, you don't have any control over that container &lt;em&gt;instance&lt;/em&gt;. Running the same "docker run" command as above is just going to spew another container instance for the same image, while the old one still stays in memory. Repeating this process multiple times is a wastage of invaluable memory and cores which isn't the goal of using docker at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="docker-logo" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1073" height="232" src="/uploads/2018/09/docker-logo-300x232.png" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more efficient way of handling things is to check the existence of a container instance already running for the image, and restart that one if required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &amp;quot;ancestor=prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; -q -l
f7261ea890ce
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above command returns the id of an already running container (if any), so using that you can just restart that same container without passing all the parameters again as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker start -i f7261ea890ce
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can automate this whole process by writing a single bash script called &lt;em&gt;start_container:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt; 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;imgid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ancestor=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -q -l&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -z &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;creating new instance for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  docker run -it -e &lt;span class="nv"&gt;AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;test&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class="nv"&gt;AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;test&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; --net&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;host &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; /bin/bash
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;instance found&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  docker start -i &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ancestor=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -q -l&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just replace the \$&lt;em&gt;imgname&lt;/em&gt; variable with that of your own image name, and pass any arguments you want (for example, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;-e AWS_KEY_ID&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;) to the container on line 7. This script will start a new container only if none are found already, otherwise, it will just restart an existing one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you find this useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Docker"></category><category term="Linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Docker is the best thing to happen to Linux since the GNU bread</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/09/docker-is-the-best-thing-to-happen-to-linux-since-the-gnu-bread.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-13T09:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-13T09:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-09-13:/blog/2018/09/docker-is-the-best-thing-to-happen-to-linux-since-the-gnu-bread.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has become an oft-repeated cliche now that docker has become the latest buzzword, both in DevOps circles as well as the open source community. But being the ever cynic and contrarian, I wasn't quite convinced of its merits and until quite recently, I thought it was just another hype …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has become an oft-repeated cliche now that docker has become the latest buzzword, both in DevOps circles as well as the open source community. But being the ever cynic and contrarian, I wasn't quite convinced of its merits and until quite recently, I thought it was just another hype that will come and go like all other things.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, software configuration management has been going on nicely without these kinds of virtualization tools since ages, and since I can install and configure php/python/apache/nginx/whatever on any given LAMP box, and there is already virtualbox to create a parallel LAMP setup on my laptop, why exactly do I need docker?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some months ago, I came to understand that the contributors to the docker project included some of the biggest industry leaders such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Docker_(software)#Adoption"&gt;Google, Microsoft, IBM, Cisco and Red Hat&lt;/a&gt;, and Linux is their primary development platform! Now, all of these professional companies couldn't have possibly bet on the wrong horse, isn't it? So, I got interested and started exploring a bit more about docker and learned that it sat somewhere between pure hardware virtualization like VirtualBox/VMWare and the slow software emulation like QEMU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, docker uses existing linux tools and libraries like iptables, apparmor, SELinux and libvirt to create an efficient solution for containerized running of your apps. This parallel environment is called &lt;strong&gt;container&lt;/strong&gt;, and unlike the other parallel environment called VMs, a container is a lot more efficient and conservative of resources (memory and cores), since it doesn't have to emulate or churn up an entirely new virtual kernel or operating system. The isolation is there at the application level, not at the operating system level which is exactly the need of the hour in about 90% of use cases for software engineers. I think the below diagram illustrates this point very well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Docker Containers vs Virtualbox VMs" height="491" src="https://www.docker.com/sites/default/files/styles/large/public/compare/docker-containerized-and-vm-transparent-bg.png?itok=nyQG8a_p" width="1200"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker Containers vs Virtualbox VMs (&lt;em&gt;Image Source: &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com"&gt;Docker.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emulating a system or running an app in a jailed or containerized environment is just one use case of docker, another and probably more popular use case is &lt;strong&gt;deployment&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;integration testing&lt;/strong&gt;. The advantage of using containerized deployment is that you don't actually have to install php and nginx to run wordpress, you don't actually have to install python and flask to run a flask app!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the developer does is builds a docker &lt;em&gt;image&lt;/em&gt; (of which a container is an instance) and your image can derive from and add reference to one of the several official pre-built ones on the docker hub such as &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/python/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/php/"&gt;PHP,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/nginx/"&gt;nginx&lt;/a&gt;, etc. All a developer has to do is define a thing called &lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/"&gt;DockerFile&lt;/a&gt; (the source code used to build an image), add reference to Python or whatever (there are variants like &lt;em&gt;python:slim&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;python-\&amp;lt;version&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to take care of specific cases), add his source code files (including &lt;em&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/em&gt; to pull the packages from pypi if need be), build, run, test and push the container to the &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com"&gt;docker hub&lt;/a&gt; and be done with it! The developer runs a container which is entirely self-contained and entirely separated from his actual system. You don't need to have python, php or any of the image dependencies on your actual system, you've developed your entire application without installing a single software on your system, and without resorting to heavy parallelization tools like VMs, can you even imagine how magical that feels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the developer pushes the image to docker hub, the DevOps or sysadmin can pull that image from there and install it on his production, testing or whatever cloud instance and just run it. Without any single configuration change, the container will run exactly as it ran on developer's environment which is just magically innovative! You've essentially abstracted away your application development and deployment to such an extent that its no longer necessary for developer and DevOps to communicate or agree on any conventions, or even know each other at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The separation of concerns between a docker container or image, and the underlying linux system is what does this whole magic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Docker Engine Components" class="size-full wp-image-1053" height="385" src="/uploads/2018/09/docker-engine-components-flow.png" width="492"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker Engine Components&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker runs as a systemd service or daemon on your linux system and is responsible for keeping this separation intact and basic errands like building an image from DockerFile, running a container from the image, list down, track and clean images and containers, push images to docker hub, etc. And all this happens using a single docker command which is easy to grasp once you start using it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;## List CLI commands
docker
docker container --help

## Display version and info
docker --version
docker version
docker info

## Execute image
docker run hello-world

## List images
docker image ls #or docker images

## List containers (running, all, all in quiet mode)
docker container ls
docker container ls --all
docker container ls -aq
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, an entire tutorial on docker is out of scope for this article, but I'd like to leave some useful links to help you install, learn and use it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com"&gt;Docker Official Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/install/linux/docker-ce/ubuntu/"&gt;Installing Docker Community Edition on Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/resources/what-container"&gt;What is a Docker Container&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.docker.com/get-started/part2/"&gt;Getting Started With Containers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com"&gt;Docker Hub (The Docker equivalent of Github)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Docker"></category><category term="Linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Beware of Uber's vomit fraud when booking a cab next time</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/07/beware-of-ubers-vomit-fraud-when-booking-a-cab-next-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-24T10:51:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-24T10:51:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-07-24:/blog/2018/07/beware-of-ubers-vomit-fraud-when-booking-a-cab-next-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to some recent reports by top technology blogs, Uber drivers have been reportedly engaging in an activity called "vomit fraud". Basically, Uber (and many other cab services too) allow their drivers to collect a fine of up to \$150 if their customer creates a mess in the cab (such …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to some recent reports by top technology blogs, Uber drivers have been reportedly engaging in an activity called "vomit fraud". Basically, Uber (and many other cab services too) allow their drivers to collect a fine of up to \$150 if their customer creates a mess in the cab (such as puking).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we aren't talking about the occasional real puke or vomit here, drivers are reportedly exploiting this feature to fraudulently claim a "cleaning fee" even when no such thing was done by a customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bmw-car-driving" class="alignnone wp-image-994 size-medium" height="200" src="/uploads/2018/07/bmw-car-driving-13781-300x200.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, according to &lt;a href="https://gizmodo.com/ubers-vomit-fraud-sounds-worse-than-surge-pricing-1827797566"&gt;this Gizmodo report&lt;/a&gt; a Miami resident was recently fined twice fraudulently for this. And whilst you might recover this fine by engaging with their customer care and maybe exchanging several emails with them, the process is almost infinitely tedious and there isn't a guarantee that you may get your money back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make things worse, as per this &lt;a href="https://mashable.com/2018/07/23/uber-vomit-fraud"&gt;Mashable report&lt;/a&gt;, a tech savvy driver may also photoshop a fake picture of a puke and provide it as evidence thus making your chances of recovering the fine almost zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice has become so rampant that the drivers are openly admitting doing this on social media platforms and treating it casually. From the linked Mashable report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&gt;&gt; &lt;em&gt;"lol vomit fraud is the oldest trick in my book," one Redditor — with &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/lyftdrivers/comments/8cdg8k/lyft_pickup_changed_rerouting/"&gt;a history&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uberdrivers/comments/8b9olz/just_announced_rate_increases_for_drivers/"&gt;ride-hail related&lt;/a&gt; posts — &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uberdrivers/comments/910kt8/its_called_vomit_fraud_and_it_could_make_your/e2v96m7/"&gt;wrote in r/uberdrivers&lt;/a&gt;. "I’ve successfully done it many times when [passengers] are rude, slam my doors, or make me wait too long. Makes them learn the hard way."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what could be the solution to this other than some basic "street-smartness" by customers and maybe the built-in review system. If drivers who indulge in such fraudulent behavior are reported frequently and called upon by customers in their reviews, that should ideally purge the system of bad drivers in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Uber"></category></entry><entry><title>Its an eerie world where tech giants can simply ban the plebeians into a digital exile</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/07/its-an-eerie-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-14T18:13:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-14T18:13:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-07-14:/blog/2018/07/its-an-eerie-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today morning, I came across &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jacksoncunningham/digital-exile-how-i-got-banned-for-life-from-airbnb-615434c6eeba"&gt;this medium post&lt;/a&gt; from Jackson Cunningham in which he describes how AirBnB simply banned him for life from their website without a due process. Jackson's mistake:&lt;!--more--&gt; He and his girlfriend rented an apartment with a rude host who came in barging in an hour before …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today morning, I came across &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@jacksoncunningham/digital-exile-how-i-got-banned-for-life-from-airbnb-615434c6eeba"&gt;this medium post&lt;/a&gt; from Jackson Cunningham in which he describes how AirBnB simply banned him for life from their website without a due process. Jackson's mistake:&lt;!--more--&gt; He and his girlfriend rented an apartment with a rude host who came in barging in an hour before the checkout time and started forcing them out, and Jackson later wrote a review about it on Google (the AirBnB's own website didn't accept a negative review about a host as its their usual practice):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="google review of jackson cunningham" class="alignnone size-full" height="487" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*ZiRvqmzxuAljq3Fy" width="652"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Jackson isn't alone who has faced the wrath of this tech giant. As the top comments on &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/8yk1rp/digital_exile_how_i_got_banned_for_life_from/"&gt;this reddit post&lt;/a&gt; corroborate, many others who tried to rent through AirBnB have faced a similar consequence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/8yk1rp/digital_exile_how_i_got_banned_for_life_from/e2bqq3p/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/8yk1rp/digital_exile_how_i_got_banned_for_life_from/e2bv3xx/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/8yk1rp/digital_exile_how_i_got_banned_for_life_from/e2c5z36/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The broader philosophical question is how easy it has become for the large tech giants of the world to simply place a plebeian or commoner into a digital exile by one flip of a switch today. The problem isn't that a company like AirBnB is able to ban a user, the problem is that people have allowed AirBnB to become a kind of digital monopoly that is able to ruin one's earnings, employment and service availing for life by simply banning them. Its the people who have given them this power, or in other words, the plebeians have brought this upon themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as much as one would try to rationalize this as a natural result of capitalism, it isn't. This goes totally against the principle of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laissez-faire"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laissez-faire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (French for &lt;em&gt;let-go&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;free trade&lt;/em&gt;) which forms the very basis of capitalism. So, even from the perspective of capitalism, banning a market agent without a due process in this way and putting them out of business goes totally against the spirit of free trade and capitalism. In fact, this is more resembling of and a digital equivalent of the Gladiator-era fascism where a Roman dictator can ban or exile any plebeian of the state at their whims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Roman Dictator" class="size-full" height="429" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*lfFsZKCyj5HSvBY5" width="800"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roman Dictator (Image Source: Medium.com)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how did the Romans solved their dictator problem? That's right, they brought in democracy and civic structure, they decentralized their political system so that its divided into multiple ministries and provincial bodies now, so that &lt;em&gt;one dictator&lt;/em&gt; shouldn't be able to affect everything at his whims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same thing needs to happen in the digital world today, I'd like to see a world where there are tons of alternatives to AirBnB, Amazon, Ebay, Microsoft, Uber, etc., a world where consumers don't give all the power to a few entities, and thus screw themselves in the process. The consumers should have many alternatives, so that if one service bans them, there are a ton of others, and in order for this to happen, the open source programmers also have a large role to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a consumer should not source everything from one service by succumbing to convenience, but cultivate a habit of giving new players a chance. Why use only Amazon for shopping, also try Ebay, Flipkart, Snapdeal, AliExpress, etc. once in a while. Why use only Uber for cabbing, also try Ola, Lyft, Hailo, Meru, etc. once in a while. Remember plebeians, you are yourself responsible for the digital world you create, and each one of us is partly responsible in some way or other for Jackson's situation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Alternative "Reddit like" Social Networking Sites for the Minimalists</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/07/alternative-reddit-like-social-networking-sites-for-the-minimalists.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-10T15:01:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-10T15:01:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-07-10:/blog/2018/07/alternative-reddit-like-social-networking-sites-for-the-minimalists.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Minimalists are those netizens who prefer websites that mostly contain rich and relevant textual content (with maybe bits of images sprinkled here and here), but certainly not auto-playing videos, flashy animations, animated gifs and motion ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making an excruciatingly heavy and painful website by combining all these things not only …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Minimalists are those netizens who prefer websites that mostly contain rich and relevant textual content (with maybe bits of images sprinkled here and here), but certainly not auto-playing videos, flashy animations, animated gifs and motion ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making an excruciatingly heavy and painful website by combining all these things not only take a toll on the server's back end resources, but is also a step back in the advancement of the Internet, not forward, at least in my humble opinion.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alternative &amp;quot;Reddit Like&amp;quot; Social Networking Sites" class="alignnone wp-image-901 size-medium" height="199" src="/uploads/2018/07/imac-apple-mockup-app-38544-300x199.jpeg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its quite evident that we are the minority because all popularity metrics point towards non-minimalist social sites like Facebook, Twitter, Google Plus, etc. And to add to that agony, &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; has also decided to follow along the path of those other sites as we are being shunned to the &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com"&gt;old Reddit&lt;/a&gt;. Old Reddit is not just being shunned as legacy, but also in the process of being dismantled. That's because any new visitor who visits a subreddit will always be shown the new interface by default (even if the subreddit owners/mods happened to have created it on old Reddit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, the user is also being gently prodded on to embrace the new version by various measures. For example, the default profile page of the user is the new profile page (even when visiting old.reddit.com, yeah!) and the only way to switch back to the older version is a small hidden switch in the preferences section that you wouldn't know exists unless you go there and scroll to the absolute bottom of the page!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reddit Hidden Legacy Switch" class="size-full wp-image-892" height="463" src="/uploads/2018/07/reddit_hidden_legacy_switch.png" width="1051"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reddit Hidden Legacy Switch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar tone, when you logout from Reddit in order to log back in (using a different alt which is quite common on Reddit), you'll suddenly find that you are back in the new version and the header link and everything else points to the www.reddit.com, and not old.reddit.com! You'll be surprised to find that even if you switched your profile back to the legacy mode, other Redditors who visit your profile will still see the new version there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Reddit is trying to send us a clear message: Fall in line with our new system or just get lost. And get lost we will, but the question is where? Certainly not Facebook, Twitter or Google Plus because that's not what a minimalist will want to use, even though they may have an account on one of these other sites just for being compatible with their non-minimalist friends, relatives, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I'm going to describe a few such social networking sites which are relatively minimalist, though all of them may not have the same charm as the good old Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, lots of minimalist sites are either getting closed or turning into micro-niches that nobody except a certain section want to use. For instance, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsvine"&gt;News Vine&lt;/a&gt; shut down recently, it was a collaborative journalistic platform where users contributed all kinds of stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also used to like &lt;a href="https://voat.co/"&gt;Voat&lt;/a&gt; very much, but recently there have been &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/SubredditDrama/comments/3gerlv/is_voat_becoming_reddit_for_racists_or_is_that/"&gt;reports that Voat is turning into a meeting place for right wing supremacists and those who like to troll online users based on their caste/ehtnicity.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/StumbleUpon"&gt;StumbleUpon&lt;/a&gt; was also recently shut down and transformed into something called Mix, I don't quite like the looks of the new design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still seems to be some hope left as some minimalist sites do exist to fill this void:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I. &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hacker News" class="size-full" height="386" src="https://i1.wp.com/beebom.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Y-Combinator1.jpeg?w=596&amp;amp;ssl=1" width="596"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacker News (Image Source: &lt;a href="https://beebom.com/reddit-alternatives/"&gt;https://beebom.com/reddit-alternatives/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Hacker News is a niche site for the technology nice, it sill tops my list because it is almost as minimal as you could get. Its a purely textual content site with neither images nor CSS transitions and perhaps that's how most of the technologists like it. The content quality on this site is also highly vetted and top notch, and definitely better than many popular subreddits where politics comes into the mix every now and then as the mods try to sneak in their own propagandas in the subreddit content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;II. &lt;a href="https://slashdot.org/"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Slashdot" class="size-full" height="346" src="https://i2.wp.com/beebom.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Slashdot-1024x553.jpeg?resize=640%2C346" width="640"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slashdot (Image Source: &lt;a href="https://beebom.com/reddit-alternatives/"&gt;https://beebom.com/reddit-alternatives/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two reasons to include &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slashdot"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;in the list. Firstly, its a minimalist site, and secondly, it is owned by BizX LLC, the same company who acquired SourceForge after the huge fiasco in Jan, 2016. If most media reports are to be believed, the new owners are doing a great job of rebuilding SourceForge from its old tarnished image. The site design is also much better than the heavy ones like Google Plus, Facebook and Quora, Slashdot is also very light on loading server resources (HTML/CSS/JS) which I like a lot. Sites like Slashdot who strive to improve the user experience and UI efficiency like this deserve all the users in the world, yet its a funny world where these other heavy sites get all the attention! So, whom I should blame if not the users who visits these sites?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;III. &lt;a href="https://hubski.com/"&gt;Hubski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hubski" class="size-full" height="309" src="https://d2.alternativeto.net/dist/s/1b468ae2-3c92-e111-8e48-0025902c7e73_1_full.png?format=jpg&amp;amp;width=1600&amp;amp;height=1600&amp;amp;mode=min&amp;amp;upscale=false" width="552"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hubski (Image Source: &lt;a href="https://alternativeto.net/software/hubski/"&gt;https://alternativeto.net/software/hubski/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hubski was something that was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubski"&gt;designed from the ground up to be a Reddit Alternative&lt;/a&gt;, so it won't disappoint you if you are looking for an alternative to Reddit. Hubski was started by Mark Katakowski as a clone of Hacker News, and the code is still in a Lisp dialect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IV &lt;a href="https://boards.4chan.org"&gt;4chan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="4chan" class="size-full" height="298" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/c/c8/4chan_main_page_2_january_2018.png" width="334"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4chan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4chan is also a minimalist site like Reddit, but geared more towards Internet activism groups like Anonymous. A redditor should feel comfortable with their discussion thread UI which reminds you a bit of the old PHP bulletin boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://snapzu.com"&gt;V. Snapzu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snapzu" class="wp-image-909 size-large" height="276" src="/uploads/2018/07/snapzu.com_-1024x484.png" width="584"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snapzu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snapzu is just like Reddit, only it has a more polished interface and they call their category pages "tribes" instead of subreddits, for instance &lt;a href="https://snapzu.com/t/technology"&gt;/t/technology&lt;/a&gt; is the technology tribe. However, you need to request an invite before joining, but apparently they dish them out pretty quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;VI. Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mastodon" class="wp-image-913 size-large" height="271" src="/uploads/2018/07/mastodon-1024x475.png" width="584"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mastodon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastodon is yet another great site, not as minimal as reddit or slashdot, but much better than facebook and twitter. And the best thing is that its federated, so mastodon.social isn't the only instance, there are a &lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;bunch of others&lt;/a&gt; too and they are all synced and federated in real time, whatever instance you be on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quora.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VII. Quora&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Quora" class="size-full" height="289" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/2/2f/Quora_screenshot.jpg" width="343"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quora (Image Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, Quora isn't exactly minimal and I wasn't even going to include it in this list, but since we have so few (working) options left, Quora needs a place here at least temporarily. At least, its way too minimal than the likes of Facebook and Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VIII. Medium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Medium" class="size-full" height="329" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/f5/Medium_screenshot.png" width="302"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium (Image Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I included Quora, I thought why not Medium. To be honest, sites like Quora and Medium fall in the far end of minimalist sites and we are stuck with them only because of lack of options. Nevertheless, the content quality on Medium is quite good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update on 16th July, 2018&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I came across one more strong contestant in the race for Reddit alternatives, its called &lt;a href="https://raddle.me/"&gt;Raddle.me&lt;/a&gt;. It was built during September last year by some &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/zm3wbj/radical-leftists-built-their-own-reddit-after-it-banned-them"&gt;"radical leftists" who felt that Reddit had wrongly banned them&lt;/a&gt;. Raddle.me does have a leftist bias, just as Voat has a rightist bias, but the interface and looks are pretty much what a minimalist Redditor will appreciate. Also, the site is built using PHP (Symfony and Doctrine), unlike Reddit which is built using Python (Pylons framework).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Raddle.me" class="size-full wp-image-948" height="641" src="/uploads/2018/07/raddleme.png" width="1366"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raddle.me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reddit"></category><category term="Social Networking"></category></entry><entry><title>Why GPL isn't working - the Freedom vs Convenience Debate</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/why-gpl-isnt-working-the-freedom-vs-convenience-debate.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-29T15:02:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-29T15:02:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-06-29:/blog/2018/06/why-gpl-isnt-working-the-freedom-vs-convenience-debate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What distinguishes &lt;strong&gt;GPL&lt;/strong&gt; from other freedom licenses is their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License"&gt;premise&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GNU General Public License (GNU GPL or GPL) is a widely used &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software_license" title="Free software license"&gt;free software license&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;strong&gt;guarantees&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End_user" title="End user"&gt;end users&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;freedom to run, study, share and modify the software&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPL or &lt;em&gt;copyleft&lt;/em&gt; strives for the freedom of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What distinguishes &lt;strong&gt;GPL&lt;/strong&gt; from other freedom licenses is their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License"&gt;premise&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GNU General Public License (GNU GPL or GPL) is a widely used &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software_license" title="Free software license"&gt;free software license&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;strong&gt;guarantees&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End_user" title="End user"&gt;end users&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;freedom to run, study, share and modify the software&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPL or &lt;em&gt;copyleft&lt;/em&gt; strives for the freedom of the plebians of the community, and guarantees them absolute freedom on the source code of a software to not just view it, but also run and modify it, and most importantly, to share it with whoever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the real world, the plebians don't want freedom, they want functionality and convenience. If a closed-source solution gives them the convenience to do a task with least efforts, they are happily going to embrace that solution despite knowing that both their privacy and freedom is at stake by using that solution. The proof of this fact is usage and popularity metrics of many such apps. For example, almost everyone knows about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal"&gt;Facebook-Cambridge Analytica privacy scandal&lt;/a&gt; that happened recently, and yet how many people switched to open and freedom respecting platforms like &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/s/social/"&gt;GNU/Social&lt;/a&gt; after that? Ask your friends about them and there is a good chance that 9 out of 10 would not have even heard about platforms like Mastodon and GNU/Social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its the same situation with messengers too. For instance, &lt;a href="https://jitsi.org/"&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt; is a freedom respecting messenger software and yet people use only &lt;strong&gt;Skype&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/strong&gt; for messaging. Not only are Skype and WhatsApp closed-source applications, their &lt;a href="https://lifehacker.com/stop-using-whatsapp-if-you-care-about-your-privacy-1825719172"&gt;problems with privacy and security&lt;/a&gt; are also well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason attributable to this situation is lethargy and laziness - people just don't want to step into the shoes of power-users or even try and learn a new tool. And as for those power-users, they do occasionally experiment with freedom respecting software, but can't make a permanent switch because of compatibility - you can't convince your entire friend circle to switch to Jitsi and Mastodon overnight, can you? If you press too much, then they'll cut off the friendship and isolate you. And though you may end up with some freedom respecting messenger software, there will be no friends left to message if you go that route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward, freedom friendliness is going to be a very important attribute while choosing a software or even a hardware for us netizens, and the reason is the &lt;em&gt;ongoing concentration of technological power in the hands of a few&lt;/em&gt;. Its no secret that &lt;a href="https://www.prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;large tech companies are eating smaller startups&lt;/a&gt; since last several years. If history is any evidence, this concentration doesn't result in a very healthy ecosystem. If we let only a few players like Microsoft, Apple, Google and Amazon to dominate the entire digital world, then we all know that the result is not going to be good, especially for us plebians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy dose of competition should prevail in the ecosystem, only that can ensure that everybody thrives. We need more and more alternatives for Youtubes, Skypes, Facebooks and the Twitters of the world, and more importantly, people should start using them. However difficult it might be, stick with it for a while - search for popular plugins, raise bug reports on the project issue tracker, participate in user forums, contact the developers and your local open source meetups, walk that extra mile and you'll find that you've got more than a solution to your problem!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our freedom is in our hands as a community or collective bunch of people. Its up to us whether we take control back into our own hands or let the technological powers dominate us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Open Source"></category></entry><entry><title>Smyte is no more - The latest episode in the acquisition saga of Tech Giants</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/smyte-the-latest-victim-in-the-acquisition-saga-of-tech-giants.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-22T20:25:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-22T20:25:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-06-22:/blog/2018/06/smyte-the-latest-victim-in-the-acquisition-saga-of-tech-giants.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not even a month has been passed since Microsoft gave a big surprise to the world at large and the open source community by &lt;a href="https://www.prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;acquiring Github Inc.&lt;/a&gt; a few days ago, and there has been &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/06/21/twitter-acquires-anti-abuse-technology-provider-smyte/"&gt;another acquisition&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. This time, Twitter Inc. bought the well known online service &lt;a href="https://smyte.com/"&gt;Smyte&lt;/a&gt;. Smyte …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not even a month has been passed since Microsoft gave a big surprise to the world at large and the open source community by &lt;a href="https://www.prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;acquiring Github Inc.&lt;/a&gt; a few days ago, and there has been &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/06/21/twitter-acquires-anti-abuse-technology-provider-smyte/"&gt;another acquisition&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. This time, Twitter Inc. bought the well known online service &lt;a href="https://smyte.com/"&gt;Smyte&lt;/a&gt;. Smyte was an online provider of anti-abuse technology services, i.e. things like AI algorithms for identifying online trolling, etc. Many customers were totally dependent on this provider's API which suddenly disappeared off the radar after Twitter Inc. acquired them yesterday.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A whole lot of customers and other depending services were affected because of this &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/seldo/status/1009873821141118976?s=09"&gt;including npm&lt;/a&gt;, the popular Node.js package manager. As usual, &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; was one of the first places where people turned up to know what's going on and update their statuses. As one of the comments quite intelligently notes, this is a very good lesson on this modern web development way that involves depending on a zillion external services and leaving your application open to the whims of acquisitions and centralization of technology powers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;::: {.reddit-embed data-embed-media="www.redditmedia.com" data-embed-parent="false" data-embed-live="true" data-embed-uuid="5bebab31-c06c-4d2c-bbd0-d938f9f97409" data-embed-created="2018-06-22T14:47:54.034Z"}
&lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/e13j9tx/"&gt;Comment&lt;/a&gt; from discussion &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/"&gt;Reminder that external dependencies can shut down without notice&lt;/a&gt;.
:::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://www.redditstatic.com/comment-embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Twitter was also filled today with tweets of complains from existing Smyte customers who have suddenly stopped receiving any communication from their service provider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/arthens/status/1009925187364458496&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Ashkenas, the inventor of famous Backbone.js and Underscore.js JavaScript libraries expressed his feelings in a very sarcastic tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/jashkenas/status/1010014139320680449&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what was Twitter's intention before acquiring Smyte, but the way this is going on, this has to end in only one of the two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Either developers take lessons from these incidents and stop depending so much on layer-2 solutions and external dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Technology giants become a bit more empathetic to the needs of smaller businesses and understand that just acquiring other services isn't a solution to the innovation problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Open Source"></category><category term="Twitter"></category></entry><entry><title>Its high time we find alternatives to centralized platforms like Youtube, Patreon and Twitter</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/01/its-high-time-we-find-alt-to-centralized-platforms-like-youtube-patreon-and-twitter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-27T07:39:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-01-27T07:39:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2018-01-27:/blog/2018/01/its-high-time-we-find-alt-to-centralized-platforms-like-youtube-patreon-and-twitter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was listening to this &lt;a href="http://www.jupiterbroadcasting.com/120622/peer-pressure-lup-227/#comments"&gt;Linux Unplugged podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized to what extent we have been locked in by the so-called "platforms" already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only few days ago, Google started blocking some of Amazon's videos on Youtube only because Amazon refused to sell Nest Cams and Chromecasts …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was listening to this &lt;a href="http://www.jupiterbroadcasting.com/120622/peer-pressure-lup-227/#comments"&gt;Linux Unplugged podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized to what extent we have been locked in by the so-called "platforms" already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only few days ago, Google started blocking some of Amazon's videos on Youtube only because Amazon refused to sell Nest Cams and Chromecasts on their website among other things.&lt;!--more--&gt; Similarly, if you have been following &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/BryanLunduke/videos"&gt;Bryan Lunduke's Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; on Linux, you may have heard him complaining about Google trying to censor his monetization of any content that relates to "Linux".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, you may have heard stories about Twitter and Facebook too about how they sometimes actively try to censor content that doesn't match up to their political agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all these cases, its the common individual who is made to suffer. In the good old days of 1990s, it was Microsoft who used to give a tough time to open source and libre folks using things like Internet Explorer and OEM deals to stop Linux, but these days, that role has been taken over by these platforms who are slowly trying to become walled gardens in their own rights, to which they can control access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the famous saying goes, "Power corrupts and absolute power corrupts absolutely". If we let these platforms continue their monopolies, it won't take long for them to do more sinister things that will hamper free speech and people's freedom. As free-thinking individuals, its our duty to find, use and support open source alternatives to these platforms. Of course, there are many open source projects who are helping us with that, all we have to do is support them in whatever way we we can. But at the very least, we can start by using these services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source Twitter Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mastodon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Mastodon is a decentralized version of Twitter. Which means that unlike Twitter (which has a single platform called Twitter.com), Mastodon is decentralized across multiple nodes, you can join any of them (or even start your own!). All nodes are federated of course, which means irrespective of which node you sign up on, you can see all the content, and connect with anybody on the Mastodon network. You can give it a try by signing up on &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;Mastodon.social&lt;/a&gt;, a popular node that I've been using since quite a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://matrix.org/"&gt;Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Matrix is an "open network for decentralized communication". Though I haven't used it personally, it seems to be a decentralized social platform along similar lines as Mastodon (Let me know in comments if you've used it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distinct advantage of decentralized platforms like Mastodon and Matrix is that there is no giant corporation to censor your free speech, or collect private data on you. The decentralized nodes are run by people like you and me, so they are like the Linux who is standing up against all the walled platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source Patreon Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.liberapay.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liberapay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Liberapay is a freedom friendly implementation which can act as a replacement for Patreon, a popular platform for open source contributors to get donations from their patrons. Patreon has been behaving quite odd lately (increase in transaction fees, network problems, etc.), hence Liberapay deserves a mention as an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dash.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Dash is a crypto currency platform that might also help in switching over from Patreon. Its built along similar lines to the Bitcoin, but has two mining layers instead of one. Using the Dash platform isn't necessarily important, the point here is that a crypto currency can be used instead of regular ways of funding for open source projects, alternatives like Bitcoin, Litecoin, etc. can also be used of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source YouTube Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Chocobozzz/PeerTube"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PeerTube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; PeerTube uses &lt;a href="https://github.com/webtorrent/webtorrent"&gt;WebTorrent&lt;/a&gt;, a JavaScript (browser accessible) version of the Bittorrent client to make peer-to-peer video streaming possible using the Bittorrent protocol. In other words, it is an "open platform" version of YouTube, a chance to escape its walled garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to add more open platforms in comments if you know about them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Twitter"></category><category term="Youtube"></category><category term="Open Source"></category></entry></feed>