<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri - Freelance Programmer - Uncategorized</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/feeds/uncategorized.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prahladyeri.com/</id><updated>2015-06-25T21:36:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Is Sourceforge.net safe anymore to download software</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2015/06/is-sourceforge-safe-anymore.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-25T21:36:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-06-25T21:36:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2015-06-25:/blog/2015/06/is-sourceforge-safe-anymore.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard about all the recent buzz surrounding the sourceforge.net website hosting adware/malware bundled installers and naive users falling prey to it. In some cases, SF even actively took control of &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2015/05/sourceforge-grabs-gimp-for-windows-account-wraps-installer-in-bundle-pushing-adware/"&gt;abandoned developer accounts&lt;/a&gt;. to bundle their crapware.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sourceforge Logo" src="/uploads/old/sf-logo.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is it safe anymore to go to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard about all the recent buzz surrounding the sourceforge.net website hosting adware/malware bundled installers and naive users falling prey to it. In some cases, SF even actively took control of &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2015/05/sourceforge-grabs-gimp-for-windows-account-wraps-installer-in-bundle-pushing-adware/"&gt;abandoned developer accounts&lt;/a&gt;. to bundle their crapware.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sourceforge Logo" src="/uploads/old/sf-logo.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is it safe anymore to go to this site and download your favorite FLOSS software? The TLDR version is NO, unless you happen to trust the developer and the project is actively being developed by them. But to understand the big picture, you will have to see the root cause of this which goes much deeper than just sourceforge, and relates to software distribution practices in the Microsoft Windows world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What went wrong?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software Development consists of two important phases: Authoring of source code, and secondly, the build process where the code is compiled to binaries and bundled into installable packages that you may download. Many years ago, sourceforge was one of the rare sites that provided a place on the internet where open source developers can host their code and binaries, and users can download them. This used to go well for many years and thus sourceforge gained a nice reputation in the FLOSS Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But soon enough, Sourceforge decided to cash in on this reputation by breaching this trust. And they started bundling adware and crapware to the developer builds. In some cases, &lt;a href="https://forum.filezilla-project.org/viewtopic.php?t=30240"&gt;the lead developers&lt;/a&gt; were in cohorts with Sourceforge. And as &lt;a href="http://www.thewindowsclub.com/safe-software-download-sites"&gt;this Windows Club article&lt;/a&gt; succintly explains, Sourceforge wasn’t alone in this. There were many othere like CNET.com, Download.com, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the adware bundling is optional in theory, the default options are so tactfully placed that only the shrewdest of hackers can dodge all of them! Though this kind of behavior is sort of expected from B-grade sites like CNET and download.com, Sourceforge was something that the open source community held in high esteem. Though most of the developers have moved to github now, souceforge was once considered the Jerusalem for downloading FLOSS Software, especially Windows Software. Even today, their interface is the best suited for novice users who are just looking for a big green download button to click - Github interface is more geared towards developers and generally overwhelms them. But now that the Jerusalem folks have turned into heretics (for lack of a better analogy), what are our options?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best option is to get it from the developer’s site itself if they provide it. But sometimes that’s not possible as the developer may not always have bandwidth to host the binaries, and we have to depend on 3rd party sites like sourceforge. As the author of the linked article suggests, &lt;a href="http://majorgeeks.com"&gt;MajorGeeks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://softpedia.com"&gt;Softpedia&lt;/a&gt; are generally clean in my experience. Downloading software from those cleaner sites, however, is just a workaround and doesn’t solve the larger structural problem of Software Distribution in Windows world. So, what is that solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Linux Solution!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One crisis we are facing in the Windows FLOSS world right now is the Middleman problem. The original developer (A) writes some code and compiles it, the middleman (SF) bundles adware to it and makes a quick buck, whilst an innocent user (B) clicks that download link. Since there is no way for B to verify if the package is actually bundled by A, SF continues to get his commissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if there was a way for B to verify if the package is actually signed by A? In the Linux world, we do have such a mechanism, so there is no place for middlemen to make a profit there. If I download GNU Emacs from the &lt;a href="http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/emacs/"&gt;GNU ftp server&lt;/a&gt;, all I have to do is &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;gpg --verify emacs.sig emacs.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; and the system will tell me whether my emacs copy is signed by developers of Emacs, or was it tampered with for injecting any malware!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second crisis the Windows FLOSS is facing is lack of a decent package management system. In above analogy, we can’t expect B to personally verify each downloaded software against A’s signature, s/he needs a good package manager that downloads the package from a trusted server and installs it afer verifying the signatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Linux world, we have two major packaging systems known by the name of &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;yum&lt;/code&gt;. How are they better, stable and secure than the Windows approach of users downloading arbitrary installers from SF-like sites and installing them, is something beyond the scope of this article. But suffice it to say that its very very high time that Windows gets a similar package manager to take care of the present structural issues surrounding it. &lt;a href="http://www.ninite.com/"&gt;Ninite&lt;/a&gt; has tried to do something in this direction, but its a proprietary and paid solution. We need open source and something that everyone accepts as a standard. Maybe, perhaps Microsoft will take the initiative and do it themselves? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>4 Ways to share your mobile internet with a PC/laptop</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2014/12/4-ways-to-share-your-mobile-internet-with-a-pclaptop.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-20T11:47:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-12-20T11:47:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2014-12-20:/blog/2014/12/4-ways-to-share-your-mobile-internet-with-a-pclaptop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The one thing I like about the world of Linux in general and also Android is the great number of options. Unlike Windows phone, where there is only one way to perform a task (if at all there is!), android provides a richer user experience in all departments.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_tether_options.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android Tethering Options" src="/uploads/old/Android_tether_options.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The one thing I like about the world of Linux in general and also Android is the great number of options. Unlike Windows phone, where there is only one way to perform a task (if at all there is!), android provides a richer user experience in all departments.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_tether_options.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android Tethering Options" src="/uploads/old/Android_tether_options.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are traveling to some place and your laptop has lost its usual source of internet connectivity. You will naturally consider surfing the web on your cell-phone, or better still, try and find a way to share the internet on your cell-phone with your laptop, so your work won't suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The android OS supports multiple ways to perform tethering (a.k.a share your mobile internet with other devices such as laptop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;USB Tethering:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I mention this method first because it is the most power-efficient of the lot. Always try to use this method before others if you want to prioritize battery savings. The only shortcoming of this method is that you will only be able to share the  mobile internet with at most one device only (in the above example, your laptop). And of course, you will be able to keep your USB cable handy. To use this method, just hook up the USB cable to your laptop (making sure that the device drivers are installed). Then, on your cellphone, go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Settings-&gt;Tethering and Portable Hotspot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and tap on the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;USB Tethering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; option to activate it. (On your particular model, the actual setting name might differ as each manufacturer customizes android to their own liking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bluetooth Tethering:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This method is less efficient than USB tethering, but still quite efficient compared to others. Again, the disadvantage is that at most only one peer can be shared. Also, the speed will be much slower compared to Wifi and other techniques, but if 10mbps is workable for you, then this option could be a great help for you. To activate, tap on this option in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Settings-&gt;Tethering and Portable Hotspot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wifi Access Point:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This method is the most common of the lot as the concept of turning your cellphone into a Wifi access point has turned into quite a fad nowadays. However, it is also the least efficient energy wise. The advantage, of course, is that your cellphone can provide its bandwidth to multiple devices at the same time. To activate, tap on this option in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Settings-&gt;Tethering and Portable Hotspot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using a USB Dongle as Mobile broadband:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This method applies only to GSM radios (not CDMA as they are locked by providers).  Though it doesn't come under the definition of tethering, the effect is same. If none of the above methods work for you (or for some reason, you don't want to use), as an alternative, you can take out the SIM card and put it in an unlocked USB dongle (also called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WorldSIM#Data_SIM_Card"&gt;Data Card&lt;/a&gt;). Data Cards are manufactured by companies like ZTE and Huawei and unlocked versions are available in many &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Generic-Wireless-7-2Mbps-Dongle-Function/dp/B00MHAKIFI/ref=sr_1_5?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1419075706&amp;amp;sr=8-5&amp;amp;keywords=usb+data+cards"&gt;online retail stores&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>7 Reasons I would prefer an Android Phone over WP8</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2014/12/7-reasons-i-would-prefer-an-android-phone-over-wp8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-19T09:42:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-12-19T09:42:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2014-12-19:/blog/2014/12/7-reasons-i-would-prefer-an-android-phone-over-wp8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My existing phone is a &lt;em&gt;Karbonn A30&lt;/em&gt; running &lt;em&gt;Android ICS&lt;/em&gt; and my next phone is going to be an Android phone too. Both as a &lt;strong&gt;user&lt;/strong&gt; and as a &lt;strong&gt;developer&lt;/strong&gt;, I've come upon the realization that Android provides a much better user experience and overall satisfaction in mobile computing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android-WP8 Feature comparison" src="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My existing phone is a &lt;em&gt;Karbonn A30&lt;/em&gt; running &lt;em&gt;Android ICS&lt;/em&gt; and my next phone is going to be an Android phone too. Both as a &lt;strong&gt;user&lt;/strong&gt; and as a &lt;strong&gt;developer&lt;/strong&gt;, I've come upon the realization that Android provides a much better user experience and overall satisfaction in mobile computing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android-WP8 Feature comparison" src="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had briefly considered using Windows Phone once, but I've discarded that idea after giving it a trial run. Here are the 7 reasons why I would only go for a phone running the Android Operating system and not WP8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More features:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is one of the primary reasons a user buys any product, let alone a cell-phone. Android clearly wins in this department as it provides more features (out-of-the-box) compared to WP8. Just open the android settings menu and compare it to the feature-deprived WP8 settings screen to prove this to yourself. WP settings doesn't even allow you to perform basic things like:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up a custom mp3 ringtone (You need a PC with Zune software running for that.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up bluetooth options (No advanced options like bluetooth tethering )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brightness settings are only low, medium and high (whereas Android provides a slider to set a custom percentage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No built-in file manager (At least the lumia 520 I tested did not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not enough power stats (Android shows a complete run-down of what apps ate how much battery life, WP doesn't even show the exact percent of battery remaining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More options for tethering:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; One of the major reasons that I use my phone is to tether my phone's internet, so as to use it on my laptop. Android provides me three options to do this: Wifi tethering (aka Access point), Bluetooth tethering, USB tethering. WP8 only provides Wifi sharing and that too is not quite customizable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More free apps:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The Google play store is full of professional apps (many of them free, too). For instance, ES3 is a file-manager, archiver, FTP-manager and backup-manager combined. This app is not freely available on WP8 and I doubt the paid version would be having the features comparable to android version. Other examples are Terminal-IDE  (A fully-fledged IDE) and QPython (A fully-fledged programming environment!) that are both freely available on Android.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opensource technologies:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Android stack completely rests on Open source technologies. The Linux kernel, Apache Harmony and Dalvik VM are all Opensource components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supported by Google:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Another reason to go with Android is that it is actively developed and supported by Google Inc, a company whose interests directly harmonize with that of the end-users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More options for the Developer:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Even as a developer, you will have a much better time developing an Android app than a WP8 app. First of all, the development tools (EclipseADT and Android SDK) are pretty well-documented on &lt;a href="http://developer.android.com"&gt;Android Developer site&lt;/a&gt;. Secondly, these are opensource tools that run on all platforms including Linux and OSX. On the other hand, developing a WP8 app requires Windows 8 64 bit version and nothing else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;No vendor lock-in:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; As a corollary to point 4, there is no vendor lock-in when you go for Android. Because the source code of android OS is freely available from the &lt;a href="http://source.android.com"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;, you can customize it if you need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>An Introduction to Go - Elegance with Power and Simplicity</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2014/06/an-introduction-to-go-elegance-with-power-and-simplicity.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-05T12:42:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-06-05T12:42:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2014-06-05:/blog/2014/06/an-introduction-to-go-elegance-with-power-and-simplicity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst I usually try to stick with only "bread-butter" languages (i.e. php, python, java &amp;amp; C#), my last project involved the &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/appengine"&gt;Google appengine&lt;/a&gt; web app written in Google's own flagship &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28programming_language%29"&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; language.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a polyglot who is always intrigued by new languages, I couldn't help being curious about how it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst I usually try to stick with only "bread-butter" languages (i.e. php, python, java &amp;amp; C#), my last project involved the &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/appengine"&gt;Google appengine&lt;/a&gt; web app written in Google's own flagship &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28programming_language%29"&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; language.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a polyglot who is always intrigued by new languages, I couldn't help being curious about how it was coding with Go, hence I took on the project. My experience of coding with Go was so gratifying that I couldn't help but share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go has a unique blend of elegance combined with power: For coding and maintaining apps in any language, readability is a very important feature. As your project size grows bigger and bigger, this becomes more and more important. In fact, you are even prepared to sacrifice some performance gain achieved by low level languages like C to get the developer productivity achieved through more 'readable' languages like java and python. This factor partly explains why less and less programs are coded in C/C++ now and more in java. It also explains the recent popularity of python, an interpreted and relatively 'low performance' language compared to its siblings, Java and C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Go brings to the table is a graceful combination of both readability and performance. Yes, unbelievable but true! It has the compiler and the strongest type system like that of C/C++ coupled with a syntax that feels home with dynamic languages like python. It even has the simplicity that is comparable to python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Syntactically, Go is based on C++, but with lots of modifications that make it easy to use, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. No semicolons (;) to end the statements;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. No type declaration needed like C (int i=2;). In Go, types are automatically “guessed” from value (i := 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. No containing braces required statements like for and if.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example would be helpful here to grasp how Go is different and better. Consider a simple square-root calculation function in C++:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;float Sqrt(float x) {
    int z = 1.0;
    for (int i= 0; i &amp;lt; 1000; i++) {
        z -= (z*z - x) / (2 * z);
    }
    return z;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now here the same function written in Go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;package newmath&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;func Sqrt(x float64) float64 {
    z := 1.0
    for i := 0; i &amp;lt; 1000; i++ {
        z -= (z*z - x) / (2 * z)
    }
    return z
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Did you notice a few things about Go? For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Less clunkiness:&lt;/em&gt; No need of hashes, braces around the ifs/fors and no need of semicolons to end statements (some of you might argue about semicolons, saying it allows you to quickly combine multiple statements on one line, but do you realize how less readable code you are creating by doing that?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Dynamism:&lt;/em&gt; The := is a “short assignment” operator in Go, meaning that you don't need to specify its type. “z:=1.0” is certainly more elegant compared to “float z = 10;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Efficient compilation:&lt;/em&gt; Despite the dynamic nature of this language that seems to suggest an interpreted nature, Go compiles and runs as efficiently as a low-level language such as C/C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason for investing your skills in Go is that Go has &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/appengine/docs/go/"&gt;Google's backing&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, the language itself is a Google invention and Google has started implementing it in most of its projects such as the &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/appengine"&gt;Google Appengine&lt;/a&gt; cloud hosting service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A controversy that might indirectly pave the way for Go's success is the looming high-profile &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oracle_v._Google"&gt;Oracle vs Google&lt;/a&gt; lawsuit about Oracle's accusations that Google incorrectly used its copyrighted Java APIs for implementing its Android operating system. Its quite unlikely that Oracle is able to get away with its claims, but if the uncertainty regarding this stays for any time longer, its very much possible that Google will gradually start building its Android APIs in Go language slowly discarding the Java APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'm not a fortune-teller, but looking at the way things are currently positioned, Go doesn't look like a language that is going to fade anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a look at official Go docs, tutorials and a list of libraries and utilities provided in references below. Happy learning Go Language!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: If you are running a debian based linux system like ubuntu, you can install golang using the CLI:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sudo apt-get install gccgo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;References:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://golang.org/help/"&gt;http://golang.org/help/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://golang.org/"&gt;http://golang.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.google.com/p/go-wiki/wiki/Projects"&gt;https://code.google.com/p/go-wiki/wiki/Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://golang.org/doc/faq"&gt;http://golang.org/doc/faq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/appengine/docs/go/"&gt;https://developers.google.com/appengine/docs/go/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28programming_language%29"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28programming_language%29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oracle_v._Google"&gt; https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oracle_v._Google&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The REAL way to make Eclipse run faster on Ubuntu</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2014/06/real-way-make-eclipse-run-faster-ubuntu.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-02T09:57:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-06-02T09:57:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2014-06-02:/blog/2014/06/real-way-make-eclipse-run-faster-ubuntu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are still one of those people who are frustrated with the crawling speed of eclipse IDE (especially after the recent clunky releases of Juno/Kepler), then you are in good company! Most of the advice you might have read until now for speeding up Eclipse must have involved …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are still one of those people who are frustrated with the crawling speed of eclipse IDE (especially after the recent clunky releases of Juno/Kepler), then you are in good company! Most of the advice you might have read until now for speeding up Eclipse must have involved tweaking the following parameters in eclipse.ini file:&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;::: {.wp_syntax}
&lt;code class="python"&gt;-Xmn512m -Xms1024m -Xmx1024m -Xss2m -XX:PermSize=1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=1024m -XX:+UseParallelGC&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
:::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Eclipse is pretty much a RAM hungry monster, feeding it with lots of RAM should surely make it run fast, right? Wrong! Until recently I had spent a lot of time tweaking those parameters, but no substantial performance could be gained (though I have 4GB of RAM with i3 which is not a bad configuration). The main issue here is that the underlying linux won't provide the required boost to eclipse no matter whatever the parameters you provide. For instance, the system monitor shows that eclipse is only consuming 500Mb RAM, now what difference will it make if I provide 2048m to -XX:MaxPermSize?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.prahladyeri.com/uploads/2014/06/eclipse-monitor.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="System Monitor" class="size-medium wp-image-2969" src="/uploads/old/eclipse-monitor-300x236.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; System Monitor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My search lead me to another better &lt;a href="http://ubuntuguide.net/ubuntu-using-ramdisk-for-better-performance-and-fast-response"&gt;approach&lt;/a&gt; to solving this problem. If somehow we can load JDK into a shared memory or a RAM-Disk instead of it starting from the local hard-disk, both startup time and performance could be drastically improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we create a RAM-Disk on linux? Well, if you using ubuntu, then you are in &lt;a href="http://superuser.com/questions/45342/when-should-i-use-dev-shm-and-when-should-i-use-tmp"&gt;luck!&lt;/a&gt; Ubuntu has a working RAM-Disk folder called &lt;strong&gt;/dev/shm&lt;/strong&gt; that could be globally used by any application as a temporary storage. If you go to that folder, you can see lots of files stored by pulseaudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought why not copy the JDK folder to /dev/shm and provide that as a -vm parameter to eclipse. Lo and behold! Eclipse runs about 10 times faster on my ubuntu machine. Try it yourself and let me know (If you are having performance issues with Eclipse, that is..-).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The 7 "Bread and Butter" Plugins for your Wordpress blog</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2013/11/the-7-bread-and-butter-plugins-for-your-wordpress-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-27T19:09:00+05:30</published><updated>2013-11-27T19:09:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.com,2013-11-27:/blog/2013/11/the-7-bread-and-butter-plugins-for-your-wordpress-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Based on my experiments while setting up this blog, below are the 7 "bread and butter" plugins for your wordpress blog. These plugins came very handy for me and allowed me to seamlessly integrate much needed functionality in my blog without writing a single line of php code.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/database_active.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Wordpress Plugin" class="alignnone wp-image-186" height="77" src="/uploads/old/database_active.png" width="77"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/contact-form-7/"&gt;Contact Form …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Based on my experiments while setting up this blog, below are the 7 "bread and butter" plugins for your wordpress blog. These plugins came very handy for me and allowed me to seamlessly integrate much needed functionality in my blog without writing a single line of php code.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/database_active.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Wordpress Plugin" class="alignnone wp-image-186" height="77" src="/uploads/old/database_active.png" width="77"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/contact-form-7/"&gt;Contact Form 7&lt;/a&gt; (Contact Forms): &lt;/strong&gt;While designing this blog, a Contact page was one of my primary requirements. This plugin is popular and well maintained. Once installed, you will have a Contact tab on your dashboard that has a default contact-form with a short-code. You can copy-paste this short-code into any post or page of yours, and lo and behold! You have a contact form ready such as &lt;a href="http://www.prahladyeri.com/contact/" title="Contact"&gt;the one on this blog&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, you can customize the default contact-form to change the fields to suit your particular needs. By default, the form filled by the user is mailed to the admin user's email address. If you want to store the form data in the WP database in addition to that, you will have to install the &lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/flamingo/"&gt;Flamingo&lt;/a&gt; plugin along with this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/jetpack/"&gt;Jetpack&lt;/a&gt; (Multi-purpose): &lt;/strong&gt;This is what I would term the "bread-and-butter" plugin for wordpress blog owners. Brought to you by Automattic (the company behind Wordpress), this plugin provides almost every feature a blogger can think of such as:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comprehensive statistics such as hits per page/post, incoming/outoing links, referrals, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social buttons and a social-networking based comment system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email subscriptions for your blog posts and comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mobile theme that automatically streamlines your site for mobile visitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing your readers to login to your blog using their wordpress.com account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/akismet/"&gt;Akismet&lt;/a&gt; (Spam control): &lt;/strong&gt;Again, this is a "bread and butter" kind of plugin. What kind of blogger, in his right mind, will trust comments on his high-traffic blog to be spam free! Akismet is a web-service that specializes in eradicating spam. Once you install this plugin, all your comments will be scanned by this web service before they make way to your dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wordpress-importer/"&gt;WordPress Importer&lt;/a&gt; (migrating your existing wordpress blog): &lt;/strong&gt;If you are migrating your posts from another wordpress hosted blog or a wordpress.com blog (like I did), you need this plugin to import the posts that you exported from there. In fact, wordpress automatically prompts you to install this plugin when you go to Dashboard-&gt;Tools-&gt;Import to import your posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/xml-sitemap-feed/"&gt;XML Sitemap &amp;amp; Google News Feeds&lt;/a&gt; (Submitting sitemaps to spiders): &lt;/strong&gt;A well written blog must also be searchable by spiders and search-engines, so that it can send readers to your blog. Now, when you submit your blog url to the search-engines like Google or Bing, it pays to have a sitemap so that the spiders know how is your blog or website structured. After installing this plugin, an automatic sitemap url is seamlessly generated for you at http://Your-WP-URL/sitemap.xml. You can then submit this sitemap url to the search engines and thus increase the visibility of your wordpress blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/w3-total-cache/"&gt;W3 Total Cache&lt;/a&gt; (caching and performance): &lt;/strong&gt;Whilst I haven't installed this plugin myself yet, it is said to improve the performance of your blog by serving static content to your users instead of running heavy-duty php scripts that increase your backend load. This plugin is also recommended by the XML Sitemap plugin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/backup/"&gt;Backup&lt;/a&gt; (backing up your wordpress site):&lt;/strong&gt; You usually take an export of your posts from the Tools-Export menu, but if you want to backup your entire wordpress blog including the mysql database dump and all files used for hosting your wordpress blog, then this plugin is the way to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content></entry></feed>